is starting and the recording uh has
started for the meeting. I'm admitting
everybody in from the lobby. So, good
morning everybody. It does take a minute
or two for everybody from the lobby to
join in. And of course, if people are
joining a minute or two late, we will
make sure to get them admitted from the
lobby as uh as the meeting progresses.
Um and so with that, um uh I am Dr.
Dominic Zerlo and I am the director for
the center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin at the department of health
and we are here to help the department
is here to help facilitate these
meetings and to hear what people have to
say. Um and so with that this is the end
of life care committee with Dr. Larry
Leman as the chair and so I turn it over
to you Larry. Thank you.
>> Great. Thank you Dom. Thanks everybody
for making it into like another Zoom
meeting in the heat of summer here. I
appreciate that it's a challenge. Um you
know so we've had guest speakers I think
probably all of our last five or six
meetings. This one is kind of I kind of
have a plan different. It's we're
looking at what are nuts and bolts
issues. Um we're you know shooting for
at least some people to be able to start
doing end of life care end of the year
beginning next year. So have a little
list of things that are that have come
up. you know, people sometimes asking me
questions, different things, questions I
have. So, we'll share that agenda in the
in the chat and we can look at it. Um,
and I I will say that I don't have the
answers to all these questions. I just
have the questions for some of them. So,
um, Dom, I'll appreciate when when
relevant. Please, you know, drop in if
you have answers to ones. So, we really
appreciate that. And um it also is an
open-ended um agenda there, you know. So
if if you have other things that you
think are important, these are kind of
like what do I need to do, you know, to
have a psilocybin friend of life up in
January? What questions do I need
answered? So that's sort of the theme of
the day.
And let's see.
Okay.
And so I'll kind of introduce each
topic. As I say, they're they're really
discussion. These are not like things
that I necessarily have the solutions
for. So maybe [snorts] about four months
back, we presented the idea of having a
space monitor, you know, present there
as to count as sort of a second person,
not actually a fully trained
facilitator, not a licensed provider.
And we thought this was particularly
important for end of life um as people
might be going out to a house. We were
agreeing that we we always wanted there
to be two people. But the questions come
up um what's involved in that person
there that this is not a license. It's
not even a facilitator.
>> Can we can we do that and um how to make
that happen? We've talked some about the
training and the training that we talked
about was maybe like a 15-hour end of
life course that given and um some type
of an emergency psychedelic course dendo
is a possibility there. But wanted to
bring up the you know the issue just to
have discussion um you know and this is
this is sort of like if you view
yourself as the licensed provider you're
going to the house and you want to have
an assistant you know how how do we
facilitate that? Can we facilitate that?
Dom, I'll I'll point that one your
direction if you want to take a stab at
that question.
>> Uh, thank you, Larry. Actually, we're
here to hear what people have to say.
So, I'd like to actually hear what um
others think. Beautiful. So, uh, yeah,
>> credit Anita with with coming up with
this this monitor moniker. By the way,
she gets credit.
>> So, uh, it looks like we do. Oh, there
we go. Go ahead, Liz. Uh,
>> Joel, your mic has been enabled.
Welcome Joel. Good to see you here.
>> Uh, we can't hear you. Uh, are you on
mute? Are you on mute?
>> It looks like you're on mute. Just as a
reminder to everybody, once we enable
your microphone, you do still have to
unmute it on your end for us to be able
to hear.
And if not, [clears throat] we can move
to the next person and come back to you,
Joel, if uh uh if you would like to
raise your hand again once you're ready.
Ian.
>> Oh, and then Joel's hand went back up,
so I don't know if he has something, but
um I was just going to present maybe um
allow a practitioner to
deputize like a provisional license for
specific specific instances.
um that way they're still operating
under a licensed professional who is
held to ethical standards um without
necessarily needing the full engaged
training. I also recognize that um
typically in death care there is already
um other people present, a death doula,
hospice nurse, whoever it may be. Um, so
potentially allowing the
um
practitioner to deputize maybe the
hospice nurse or someone else to help
out in that process. Um, maybe would
allow
more people to assist without um
necessarily
requiring too much burdensome additional
lensure, but it's just an idea. And then
Joel to unmute in the top right hand
corner of your screen should be a little
microphone icon with a slash through it.
If you click it then you will be
unmuted.
Okay. And Joel, you'll need to unmute on
your end. Your mic is enabled on our
end.
And one thing, one other item to check
for Joel is to see if your microphone on
your computer is actually connected into
Teams. Sometimes that that happens as
well. Um, and sorry to see that you're
not able to unmute. Um, if you would
like, um, you can still put your
comments in the chat as well. Um, or
some people do find that if their
microphone is not connected, if they
drop off the meeting and then rejoin,
they're able to reconnect their
microphone.
So, you can try that as well.
Uh,
>> Chris, uh, your mic has been enabled.
>> Hi, thank you. Um, hello all. Larry, um,
you cut out I don't know if it's my end
or your end, but I just want to make
sure what your question was. Is this is
this providing psilocybin services in
the home,
Chris? Um, potentially it could be
either way. I mean potentially this
person could be functioning um in a
service center or an office but I think
particularly we had talked about it um
to going home and so you know I think I
would view as an assistant to the uh to
the licensed provider who's going to the
home.
>> Okay. So there would always be um a
licensed provider and they would be the
the the support person. Um well this
this is my my belief. I think that
individual could be a wide range of of
um professions or or even a home health
care aid that is not necessarily trained
in psychedelics, but they're there to
support the individual say for toileting
needs and I'm talking about if this is
in the home. I liked your space um
acronym and that was a minimum
uh number of hours to train somebody to
be an an attendant. So that that's one
thing but but yeah I I wasn't clear on
the exact question and I'm more focused
I know in the home but generally
speaking I think that second indivi
there needs to be a second individual
and I think you know that that should be
somebody that's got that minimum
training that you had talked about.
>> Yeah. Just just to loop thanks Chris.
I'm just going to loot people back. So
part of the discussion was a way to
again make these services accessible and
people felt like with the amount of
training we talked about that there
there are a lot of people like to
volunteer for hospice and other things
this could be something where um you
know people can actually volunteer and
it may not be um an extra an extra
expense in that situation. you know, in
some situations, you know, we see that
um end of life care may not be as
billable on some of the, you know, on
some of the things and certainly for the
uh, you know, for the med medication
doses. So, the idea of anything we can
do to bring the cost down. So, that was
part of we also were talking about sort
of an entrylevel position where people
might do this and then decide that they
want to go on and become a licensed
provider or facilitator.
Joel, go ahead. Your mic is enabled.
>> All right. Does it work now?
>> Yes.
>> Hallelujah. All right. I don't know what
was going on. Sorry about that.
Good morning, everybody. Um, so I
thought I'd share a little bit about
what I do as I am I'm in the space
already. I I I I offer um ketamine
therapy for end of life in the home
setting.
And I kind of reflect on the difference
between that and psilocybin. And
probably the biggest difference just
from uh mechanicals is the time.
Ketamine sessions are typically an hour
uh with there's some half an hour or so
prep before and maybe another 45
minutes. So all in all it's probably
about 45 minutes. I mean sorry 2 hours
and 45 minutes is a pretty pretty
average. I usually schedule 3 hours for
a session. Uh I think with with
psilocybin typically those are much much
longer and so I think uh cost is
something I think about um and so one I
always have somebody in the room but
it's always a family member um when I do
these sessions I think that's completely
adequate um because they're there just
really as a witness make sure that
there's no concerns of wrongdoings on my
end so it protects me. It's also another
person just to maybe help the patient
reflect after the fact after I've left
about what what has what what happened.
I do a little bit of prep for them so
they kind of know what to expect. it
doesn't take uh very long and I'm I'm
I'm worried about having to have another
person that is a paid person because it
will make this much much too expensive
as it is uh if we're looking a typical
psilocybin session between 5 to 8 hours
uh and again you never really know so
you have to schedule probably so it's a
full day um I think to keep this cost
down having one trained person and again
I don't as a physician I don't see
myself being able to do that, spend
eight hours with a patient one-on-one.
Um although I'd love to do that, that
probably seems cost prohibitive. Um but
having somebody who's trained who was
kind of under my supervision. Uh and
then the second person would be a family
member uh or maybe a hospice volunteer.
But again, I think my concern is because
these are very long sessions, having uh
somebody who has to be paid
would make this very very uh cost
prohibitive, which is something I think
we all are trying to keep the cost down.
That's my my thoughts.
>> Thank you, Joel. Ian.
>> Yeah. So, thank you, Joel. That was a
really good insight. Um, especially
given the family support system, I am
definitely one that I believe there
should be someone else in the room. I
don't necessarily think that they have
to be um, you know, highly trained and
specialized in psilocybin. Um, which
brings me back to maybe the
practitioner, whoever it is, could
deputize a like assistant or a helper.
That way, whoever already is in the
room, the death doula, the nurse, the
whoever their support system is, and it
varies across patients. Um, one of them
could just be saying, "Hey, you're going
to sit with us um for that duration."
Um, but yeah, you are correct. It is a
very long duration for someone to be um
under someone's care. So any way we can
reduce that the number of professional
hours that we have to bill for would be
incredible. Thank you.
>> Danielle, go ahead.
>> Hi, good morning everyone.
>> Hi. Good morning. Hi. Good morning. Um,
I agree with what's been said so far.
Thank you, Dr. Rosen specifically.
Rosen, I'm sorry. I'm not sure I
pronounced that. um
death doulas specifically, hospice
volunteers,
patient care assistants, all of these
folks that are already spending extended
periods of time with these patients, I
think are the perfect people to be
trained under a program like you're
talking about, Dr. Leman, whether that's
10 hours, 15 hours, 20 hours, whatever
the program is that we decide on, I
think Dr. Lita Fetmi is probably a
perfect person to look to to helping
figure out what that training program
could look like for our state. But we
can look to medical aid and dying
specifically and the way that that's
done a lot around the state, especially
in rural areas where a physician isn't
always able to be there for the actual
ingestion. And we rely on volunteers, we
rely on death doulas, we rely on family
members to mix the medications,
administer medications. So in my mind,
if we can do training around something
that is that final, that is that large
and trusted to people who are not
licensed, right? something that there's
no turning back from. I'm pretty sure
that we can figure out how to do it for
psilocybin as well.
Any
other thoughts or comments on the space
monitor?
>> If not, um the next question was
uh
>> Chris has a comment. Thank you.
Yeah. Hi again. I guess just a follow on
to what Danielle had said. Um because I
obviously I really support
that. Um and I would say, you know, you
talked about volunteers. I think New
Mexico has to air on the side of caution
in safety out the gate and to be able to
gauge whether or not um uh what what
that individual's training needs to be.
So again, I'll go back to yes, that
space attendance, 10 or 15 hours of
training, I think is um a minimum, a
mandatory.
Um I I don't know, you know, um
volunteers
I I personally should should think you
give you give the client the option. Um
and I think again to air on the side of
safety, you want somebody who is trained
[snorts] and is getting paid.
Joel, your mic is enabled.
>> Thank you. So, I I guess I I'm a little
confused because I think there's kind of
multiple things being said and I think I
just want to be clear. I agree with you
Chris that there needs to be somebody in
the room who's trained. I guess if I'm
understanding Larry your question is
using the term a space monitor which I I
have to say I don't love you know
chaperone is kind of what we typically
think about in the medical world
and and that's where I I agree Chris
that the main person and we're talking
about at least two individuals in
addition to the the patient
or the client but one p one person
should be definitely trained and I think
a 15 hour or 10 hour whatever ultimately
training process where the and making
sure this is safe is absolutely but I
think and again maybe I'm not I'm
misunderstanding you Larry but the
second person I feel pretty strongly
that should not need to be somebody
who's trained so I kind of make the
distinction between these two
individuals and we're assuming that we
are going to have two individuals um in
in the room at the time um so I just
want to make sure that I'm clear and
that is really what we're talking about
and and it's not just one person and
that they're they have distinct roles.
>> Joel, what what you're just saying is is
what was described a few months back.
And um I think we talked about more like
about 30 hours. The idea maybe a 10 to
15 hour um you [snorts] know, end of
life psychedelics course and then
something like a a um like a Zeno course
or something just on psychedelic
emergencies. So something like on the
like 30 hours on that and that would be
and that for that to be a volunteer. So
yeah, Chris, we're definitely not
talking about just leaving a volunteer
there. It was more as a second person.
You know, part of it, you know,
especially if you're talking about an
8-hour session. Um, people need to have
some time to take a break. They have
their own own biological needs. They may
need to make a phone call. So, I think
it's essential that there be a second
person. And the idea of the volunteer
was to um was to make that uh um more
more more livable for the person there
for 8 hours as Joel was describing um
and also more affordable.
Any other thoughts on that? If not,
maybe we'll move on to the next. We have
have about eight seven or eight topics
on the list here.
The next one um is just to have a
discussion about um um homebased service
like who's eligible. The the
[clears throat] current the last I saw
of the draft um um for end of life
services there would need to be I think
you know an application for for each
individual person. I think it would have
to justify that they were not able to um
you know go to a facility and such and
um I think another approach would be
just to say that end of life care is
more appropriate in the home when it can
be done and make that standard. So, I'm
throwing that open for discussion.
>> Uh, Robin, your mute is enabled. Thank
you.
>> Hi. Can you hear me?
>> Um are are you saying an application for
each individual um which then has to go
through a review process because when
we're talking about hospice, you know,
time time is very limited. So, can there
be some some kind of language or
provision that allows um hospice
patients to potentially,
you know, bypass that that review
process?
That's the question. I I I mean my own
opinion is that would be a good
approach. I think there there' be
different ways to do it. One could
define hospice um as within the last 6
months. We've when we talk about end of
life, you know, for psilocybin, we've
talked about that that maybe that may be
a much longer span. It may be somebody
diagnosed with breast cancer that may
never die of breast cancer or certainly
has multiple life. So I think that I
think there'd be a couple of different
ways to do it. One could uh say any end
of life could be at home or one could
define it as you're mentioning Robin
more in a hospice level
>> Joel go ahead
>> thank you yeah I mean I think that's
really the kind of the crux of this is
defining what end of life what do we
mean by that because I mean we we've
obviously talked about you know
including family members and other um
other scenarios and kind There's the
ideal world. Um, and then there's the
reality. And and I and I don't I'm not
sure where that lands. Um, I I I again I
I I work in the end of life and most of
my patients are in hospice and as
somebody who offers and medical aid and
dying and so that's kind of the space
that I work in. But I think as Larry
just pointed out the example of a person
with breast cancer who's going through
that process, I mean they're maybe even
getting chemotherapy or radiation and
are going to uh the hospital still.
they're not on hospice. Um they are
potentially end of life. Are they
somebody who can be qualified to go at
the home? I again so we have to kind of
define that line and I I we haven't
really I mean I would suggest that we
probably should define that before
because then it makes it easier
otherwise we're going to keep spinning
our wheels on this. So I I I'd like to I
don't know talk more about have have
that defined and that's going to make
this easier to to move forward.
And we have to make that decision. I
mean, there has to be some line
somewhere.
>> Ian,
>> hi. Yes. I'm more on the line of we
should be a little more strict with how
we define end of life. And the reason I
say that is not because I don't want to
help more patients. I think we could add
some specifics to um end of life care
like maybe their applications need to be
reviewed first cuz there's um a timeline
like we have to process um and then what
we could do for like you said the
patient with breast cancer who um ends
up making it. Right. While we could
still categorize and approve as a board
to send to the secretary um existential
distress associated with any
lifelimiting illness, which there has
been some evidence for um but I don't
know if that's necessarily specific to
today. I just know that if we allow it
to be a little bit more strict, but then
add a separate condition, we may be able
to add like acceleratory pathways um to
allow these patients to get accredited
and that kind of thing.
Thank you,
>> Candy. You're next.
and you might want to unmute yourself.
All right, I did it. Hi everybody.
[laughter]
Thank you for everything that's been
shared. And I didn't get in on the first
topic, but I absolutely think that that
the person that's with um with patients
should be have some training. I'm a
longtime hospice chaplain
and um just relocated to New Mexico.
So um I'm very eager to to talk more
about this. I uh I know from Oregon that
um an average stay on hospice is a 40
something days and it's not long enough
you know and even though somebody's
illness may be making them eligible to
become a to get on hospice service with
6 months possibly 6 months left in their
life
they don't and so I feel like that
there's a lot that can be done to help
people to face end of life
well before it's time for hospice. Um
so being able whether that's um in our
work to be able to communicate more in
the paliotative care realm and others
and like somebody said with somebody who
has breast cancer people are thinking
about it. They're thinking about end of
life and they know that's possible, but
there's not been there and from my
perspective to be able to possibly use
our work in this and the desire to face
those existential concerns and to face
it with family
>> [clears throat]
>> um would be tremendously beneficial and
actually can change the whole trajectory
of their lived experience.
the end of life and the whole trajectory
of their bereavement.
So that's my hope with this. And and by
the way, I'd love to know how to contact
some of you. And Larry, I I'm now at UNM
and I would love to connect with you.
And Dr. Rosen, I would love to connect
with you. And I'd love to know how to do
that. And I can even put my contact
information in here as well.
Thank you, Candy and Jennifer, your mic
is enabled.
>> Hi, good morning. Can everyone hear me?
>> Yes. Okay, great. Um, a few things. Uh,
I I'm in agreement with uh Dr. Rosen
about, you know, that that question of
how are we defining end of life? Um, and
um, I'm going to kind of circle around
here, but I feel like uh, this question
about reviewing the appropriateness of a
home has been coming up a few times in
our conversations and I ultimately feel
like it's a little prohibitive. Um, I
think like what are we reviewing around
that home and how do we make those
decisions? And it just feels like it
gets kind of um, clustery. And I think
that we've already got a certifying
provider that we're going to need a a
provider that is certified to do the
service.
And I think we can rely on those humans
to keep themselves safe, you know, in a
reasonable manner. We do that in hospice
all the time. Um, we get into situations
and we have to make those decisions. and
so in homes. Um,
and I like what Ian is talking about
that um, maybe we can start to define
some sort of qualifying diagnosis around
existential distress and then we have
that certifying provider that is
approving them for this service, right?
And we have certifying providers that
are deeming them, you know, as having a
terminal diagnosis already in the end of
life field. Um, and so maybe that could
just be something that is more defined
around, you know, they they have a
cancer diagnosis, you know, ultimately
that deems them having a terminal
diagnosis.
Um, and now we have a maybe a diagnosis
that is existential distress, just like
we have something that is depression or
PTSD that can qualify them to be able to
get the service in the home.
um and then relying on those providers
to make the determination that that home
setting is safe. So that's my opinion. I
feel like as we're getting into more and
more layers of um process that is
prohibitive, especially for New Mexico
and also um I feel like having to have
an assistant that I did I just didn't
weigh in on that. I think that having to
have an assistant is also prohibitive.
um as far as having to pay that person.
So, just wanted to weigh in on that,
too. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. And Robin, your mic
is enabled.
>> Uh I think just kind of echoing a little
bit about what Jennifer said, and I'm
thinking particularly in the hospice
space, 100% of our patients have already
been given a terminal diagnosis. That's
criteria to even be um enrolled in a
Medicare certified hospice. But also
just thinking about medical aid and
dying, our physicians have capability to
uh prescribe and to um to determine
competency for an eligibility for
medical aid and dying. And so, um, you
know, I I I don't see necessarily
having to, you know, the the need for
having to go through, um, an application
for those individuals. I think it's
going to become burdensome on on the
people determining um eligibility and I
think it's also going to create backlog
and then it's you know at that point is
also going to just make it more
difficult for people to access and
longer wait times for people to access.
>> Thank you Robin.
Go ahead, Sky.
>> Go ahead, Skye.
>> Can you hear me now? I was having
problems. Uh, thank you for allowing me
to be in these meetings. I've been
sitting here listening to everybody.
Joel Rosen brought up a a good point. I
put some things in chat, but I felt I
wanted to reiterate this. I have a
neighbor next door. He's a male older
person. For four years, he has been in
hospice and um
nobody can understand. I mean, he's
still, you know, he's still with us.
He's taking his medications, but make no
mistake, he's still in hospice. And
according to what Joel Rosen put into
the chat, hospice is 6 months or less.
But here we have someone who doesn't
have breast cancer. He's suffering from
something else. But
how do you determine someone like that
to be eligible who's been, you know,
dealing with this illness for quite some
time and not in a good place, I might
add. So, um, he's, you know, he's not
going to be coming back like someone
who's had breast cancer and and and God
willingly survived it. This man is just,
you know, holding on. So, um I'm
wondering if someone could address that
um in this chat in this um Zoom.
Thank you.
Thank you, Sky.
Go ahead, Denali.
>> Morning everyone. Um can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Um I am really grateful to be a part of
this conversation. I um I raised my
hand. Jennifer made a good point about
access and you know how
um
yeah limiting it can be to scrutinize
you know the appropriateness of of
inhome care. And I I just appreciate
raising that. I wanted to
um take that as a chance to
uh mention something I noticed in the
draft rules that I know are being
revised at the moment, but I I imagine
that um inh home care would fall under
the application for other approved
locations. If I'm wrong about that
assumption and someone from the
department can jump in, please do. Um
but if that is the case, there is a
requirement
of proof of ownership for the home or
place or otherwise a um signed statement
from the property owner.
And uh I'd just like to, you know, have
us reflect on how that might negatively
impact
folks who are homebound and seeking
care. I don't think in any other
circumstance it would be appropriate to
require a renter to have their landlord
approve care. So I if if that does
apply, I think we could have um a pretty
simple uh carveout for for folks who are
homebound.
>> Thank you, Danali. Chris, your mic is
ready.
Boy, lots to unpack. Larry, I know you
probably want to get to the next
questions, but um I didn't realize that
that there is this application process.
I thought it was going to be that a um a
physician, a trained physician, and I'm
not sure if it's practitioner the exact
title, um would prescribe and then that
they would then be able to work with a
clinician who would be the facilitator.
that there was no quote unquote
application process beyond that. So if
an individual found a prescriber to
prescribe and then they worked with a
clinician. Um so if it's anything
different I'd like to understand that.
Um I I think the other big distinction
I'd like to make here is there's a
difference between inhome services and
defining the end of life condition. and
Joel from previous meetings I liked what
um Larry had had sort of crafted which
is a pretty broad definition of end of
life because from my perspective
um th those individuals whether they are
just diagnosed with uh cancer or they
are really close to the end of life are
all suffering from existential distress
among other things. So to me the broader
the better but we could have just like
Colorado you know inhome services are
for anybody who is eligible or receiving
paliative care which hospice is a is
under that umbrella or they are disabled
or they're they're deemed homebound. So
you know somebody doesn't have to be um
toward the end of life in order to
receive um inhome um services.
Dr. Leman, go ahead. Thank you.
>> Oh, thanks. Um, I was going to share
just some some of my own thoughts, maybe
clarify them. Um, Chris, I think we were
talking about the approval for the at
home services, not for the approval for
um uh for the psilocybin services. like
they're they're a little different
there. I I' I'd like to make an argument
I think fairly strongly that we should
not be limiting this to people in the
last six months. I think um a lot of
what this is about I've think quoted
before saying is psychedelically
assisted living of people that have um
um existential distress from terminal
illness not not only the dying process
and the studies that have been done
actually have included that. I mean,
there's people that, you know, are alive
5 years later after the NYU and John's
Hopkins studies. The one we're doing at
UN M um allows anyone to be um for
having any um any uh [snorts] um any
cancer diagnosis other than um skin
cancer. And so I I think that we I would
really hope that we can keep keep that
broad definition that we've talked about
in the past but perhaps limit the um
limit you know the at home if we feel
there's a need to limit that to people
in paliative and hospice care that might
be one reason one way to separate that
but I I hope we don't you know go to
defining end of life as being um people
who are in hospice
Joe, go ahead.
>> Thank you. So, I want to echo what Larry
said. I completely agree that we do need
to keep this broad. I do just worry
about using the word the term pali of
care which is a service that is very
limited in our state. Even in Santa Fe
getting into pallet of care services is
very difficult and I can't imagine that
in Taos or in hobbs or in you know I
don't know Gallup that there isn't even
a pallet of care provider and again this
is of course people who are not on
hospice yet just to make clarifying the
two the distinction here. So I do think
they should be eligible for pallet of
care but they don't have to be receiving
pallet of care because they might not be
able to get it and and I don't remember
somebody mentioned the idea you know the
kind of similarities to medical aid 9
which I do a fair amount of that and I
think you know again we're given kind of
the authority to to certify a patient uh
whether they you know qualify to you
know do they have a terminal diagnosis
in that law it's it's specifically do we
think that they have a six months or
less to live and we are often wrong I
kind of post that in the in the in the
uh in the chat. I mean, I've had
patients who I certified and they lived
for a year and a half before they
underwent medical aid and dying and we
just reertified them every six months.
So, I think that is I think very
reasonable that we can we're allowed to
be wrong and and having a physician or
or medical provider. I don't think it
should be limited to physic physicians.
I think one of the nice things about our
medical aid and dying uh law is that
it's not limited to physicians. It's uh
open to nurse practitioners and
physician assistants as well, which I
think is again in a in a state with a
lot of rural areas where physicians
might not even be around. I think having
this open to to non- physicians is
important. Um so those are kind of my
thoughts about this.
>> Thank you, Joel.
>> Go ahead, Dr. Leman. Um this is a
question for um you know for uh DM or
Rob
the the section that was in the drafted
rules about needing the permission of
the landlord. Um was that done from like
a advisement from from legal? Um it does
seem like you know that these are safe
services and that you know I don't I
don't think I don't think people have to
get permission of their landlord to
receive you know IV chemotherapy if
indicated by home health. I don't know
why they should have to get their
landlord to approve their self-
assignment services.
>> Thank you Larry. Um yes, this is
actually does come to a similar
situation with other uh medications or
substances that are illegal on the
federal level and it's actually to
protect the landlord. Um and yes, it was
done with legal advisement. Um and uh so
it's really something that is there to
protect the owner of the property. Um,
one of the questions that's kind of come
up just it with regard to uh timeline
for processing the application is um we
do have to have that provision in the
rules with regard to the other locations
because the statute is clear that
psilocybin is only enters into the
protected status of the medical program
if it is done and actually utilized
within an approved location. And so that
is a part of why that aspect is there.
Just to sort of reassure everyone to
give you an idea is we have gotten very
good with how to review applications and
how to move them forward understanding
that yes we need to provide priority
especially in cases such as with end of
life. We do that currently for example
with regard to medical cannabis where uh
we are now at a point where back in 2019
the issues of backlog and issues were
very clear. Um however what we do have
or they were very clear and they would
take up to 30 days for applications to
go through. Um at this point in time
that occurs in less than a day because
we are actually able to review
applications and work through them. And
so we're going to be using similar
processes and systems with regard to the
other locations because we recognize
that time factor especially um and uh
and so those are a couple of the reasons
behind that um and with regard to that
and also to hopefully help uh alleviate
some of the concerns with having that
application. But we are required to have
an application and most of the
application portion is about safety um
and to ensure just that safety is
present. Um but we're not talking about
a lengthy application that will be
honorous for individuals to do. So I
hope that helps answer the question.
>> Go ahead Ian.
So
a little bit of concern and maybe
there's nothing we can do about it is um
actually asking for that landlord
consent. So in a lot of financial
industries intent is proved or intent is
disproved
via um an inability to know and oh you
didn't know and you couldn't have known.
So, a landlord that didn't know and
couldn't have known probably couldn't
prove the criminal intent. Um, but a
landlord who knew signed the right to
have psilocybin on his premises, that
person now is much more legally
vulnerable than uh a landlord who just
had no idea it was a tenant. it's leased
out um in that terms of regulatory and
in direct
comparison to cannabis. I understand
cannabis on the grounds that smoking can
um devalue a property and so they may
need to be known. Um, but still I can't
think of another oral medication where
you would have to ask a landlord to take
an oral med. Like that is a very
interesting proposal and it may be
legally necessary but it is very
interesting to say the least.
>> Thank you Ian. Go ahead Denali.
Yeah, thank you for the um
for the clarification from the
department. And I think I just want to
be clear. I think I'm my reading of this
is that it's intended for
um other approved locations. So
something that isn't happening within a
medical clinic and it's not just
homebound use. I think that that's kind
of the exception. Um but it is you know
like having temporary retreat centers
you know I think I think it's it's good
that the department has created a
mechanism for um approval of locations
other than um other than just a
brickandmortar
uh health center. Um, it was unclear
from um unclear to me from your
response, Dominic, if the if the
requirement would apply to homebound
patients equally. Um, and and I do think
that that would be inappropriate for it
to apply um for the reasons that folks
have have stated. I think it makes sense
to have it um for temporary use. Uh you
know when and and how it reads is is
like it's you know the the facilitator
who's the one who um would maybe be
renting. Um [clears throat] but if it's
not intended to apply to homebound
patients then I think that needs to be
explicit.
And if it is I I yeah access concerns
and you know we're we're talking about
people at the end of the life end of
life who are renters and um yeah but I'm
I'm not clear whether it is or not.
>> Okay. Thank you Robin. Go ahead.
I also do have some access concerns
because when we're talking about um
patients with mobility issues and you
know having to chase down a landlord
um I'm just I'm just imagining you know
how difficult this is is going to be for
us um to to be able to to provide access
to our patients. Um, however, you know,
if we do put this in our patient
acknowledgement that they signed that
they have notified their landlord, um,
you know, that seems more doable.
Thank you, Robin.
>> Sky, go ahead.
>> Yeah. Hi. Um,
this is just a comment. I I find it
invasive. What if someone needs the
therapy that has been legal in the state
for assisted, you know, therapy that
we're discussing and you have an HOA,
for instance, that I'm the on the board
of in Elorado and they, you know,
depending on their their views, um, they
they they feel no, we don't want this
here yet. Everybody here is smoking pot
and doing psilocybin. So I I I just feel
that someone who is needing this
medicine
and then you have to go get approval
it from people, you know, like a board
or a landlord or whatever it is. I just
find it invasive. And I'm wondering if
there's a way
um
maybe now's the time to look at changing
the the law. I mean, I don't know this,
but I I feel this discussion is is
needed because, you know, if it were me
and I needed it and my and I was
homebound, end of life, and my and I was
renting and my landlord says, "No, I
don't want this." Depending on what his
views are politically, I I don't know
[clears throat] how I'd feel about it.
Would I move? How would I move? what
would I do? So, it's just this is a
great discussion and I think it needs to
be given more thought. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Sky
Joe.
>> Wow, I think we opened up Pandora's box
here. This is kind of a hot topic.
Uh so again in somebody who's in the in
the medical aid and dying world I mean I
I do obviously all the ingestions in the
home
and that is a lethal dangerous
combination of medications. I can't even
imagine having to go to an HOA
and having to request and the HOA you
know they're stationed in Kentucky and
they're actually a religious
organization. Uh no way in hell would we
get approval. I'll take it a step
further. So we do these uh we do
ingestions in uh some of the facilities
in uh in town in Santa in Santa Fe and
in Albuquerque and we don't even let the
facility know because sometimes the
facilities have um this is done in the
patient's room in their apartment.
They are on hospice. This is completely
legal and appropriate and we don't need
permission from anybody and this is the
patient's decision. they are supported
by their families, by their hospice
team, by their physician. And so I I
feel very strongly that uh this should
not be something that the landlord
should even acknowledge. There should be
nothing in the on the consent if there's
such a thing. I mean that's it's going
to be very very difficult to get this
to happen and we're talking about access
and different kinds of providers etc. If
we have the landlord involved, I mean, I
can't imagine any medical treatment that
we have to ask the landlord for
approval. That just seems crazy,
outrageous. Um, so whatever we need, I I
would say that's a priority. If that is
already written somewhere that, you
know, and again, I make the distinction
again, this is where the treatment
occurs. And we're not talking about I'm
renting a building to do psilocybin as a
treatment center. That's very different.
We're talking about in a patient's home,
whether they rent it. I'll take it a
step further. We do medical aid and
dying in Airbnbs all the time. Um
patients who uh I I just share another
example. We had a patient who was in
Kundio right now. Uh there was a big
fire and she had to be evacuated and she
has to do this in a hotel room. Uh she's
doing medical aid dying actually
probably as we speak right this very
moment with one of my colleagues. So, I
mean, I think it's it's would be crazy
to have to ask a landlord or um or an
HOA or for again this particular end of
life
process. I'm not talking about patients
who or sorry, providers who are setting
up a a kind of a facility where they're
going to be offering psilocybin
treatment on a regular basis. I think
that's that's those are very different
scenarios in my mind. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Joe. Uh go ahead, Brenda.
>> Uh yeah, I just wanted to throw my two
cents in here because um patients are
protected by HIPPA and if we're um so
all of that is very private medical
information. So why wouldn't that be
part of uh where uh or how uh a patient
is getting uh medication? So I just
wanted to throw that out there.
question for um for Denali illegal. Um
Dom, is this something that we can help
protect against the concerns about um uh
risk landlords in the in a fix up bill?
Is there a way that we can address that?
Because it feels like there's pretty
strong opinions that this shouldn't have
to happen that way. And I I'm I'm
certainly no lawyer, so I I can't really
weigh in there, but it almost seems a
little endless to me, too. I mean, if
you have a mortgage, doesn't does the
mortgage company have have a say in
this? I'm, you know, I'm just trying to
understand what we can do to um to avoid
that clause in the in the ranks.
>> Looks like Sky has her hand up. Go
ahead.
Yeah, just one real quick thought uh as
we're discussing this.
So, you do get a hold of a landlord and
he gives the okay, wouldn't he have to
sign a paper not disclosing, well, you
know, apartment 2A is doing psilocybin
and you know, I mean, we're dealing
with, you know, the HIPPA
regulations and all. I mean, it's all
kind of one big ball of yarn here. So,
um, that would be something to consider,
I think, to, you know, I I just think
it's opening up so much and I agree with
everything Joel said and a lot of what
everybody's saying that this really
needs to be looked into. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Sky. Go ahead, Denali.
>> Yeah, I I don't know that we'll come to
a resolution um today. I we've had a lot
of conversations about the landlord
attestation.
This was something that first arose in
the propagation regulations. Um and I I
understand the department's concern both
around renters and landlords. Um, but it
is really complex and I think Ian made
the point about um, you know, when we
when we ask someone to attest to
federally illegal activity,
um, we we just it's like a de facto
prohibition because no one will do that.
Um, and so we we end up making it very
difficult for renters to participate in
this place. And I think that those
concerns are especially acute when we're
talking about renters who are the
patients. Um, so I know we've had many
conversations with the department about
the landlord issue and attestation. And
I see this that the language is iterated
a bit since propagation is how it how it
came up in these drafts. I'm more than
happy to continue to have conversations
um and and think about what the right
balance is and um maybe a discussion
with the legal department would be
helpful.
>> Thank you, Denali. Senator Steinborn,
>> thank you. Yeah, really interesting
discussion and I could see all sides,
but I think I I have real concerns with
having to get landlord approval to do
this. Um because I think you also have
HIPPA protections for people's medical
health care and you know it's just this
is such a sensitive thing. It's such a
private thing um that uh you know I
think in terms of like law and liability
the law requires this is my basic
business law 101 but the law requires
someone take reasonable care you know if
you're a landowner and you can't
possibly know that someone did
psilocybin therapy and something happens
you couldn't have known that like you
took reasonable care as a land owner I
think their legal exposure
I I think that's kind of a stretch of an
argument to say that they have to be
signed off to protect them. Um,
in my non-awyer opinion, but uh
yeah, but I do think it definitely, you
know, violates someone's privacy. I
think on the flip side of the coin, when
we needed medical cannabis, in order for
someone to have medical cannabis, I
mean, did we have people sign, you know,
get their landlord's permission to use
medical cannabis at their home? Um, so I
don't know. I I think I would really
double check with the lawyers about what
what is really the legal threat to a
landlord. Um, and are they do they
really have legal exposure? because I
think if the answer is really probably
not, then we should heir in the side of
the patient and uh protecting their
privacy and protecting their rights to
be able to seek medical care. So that's
kind of my thought on this. Thanks.
>> Thank you, Senator.
Dr. Dr. Leman, we have um many things on
the chat if you wanted to address some
of those.
>> Sure. Just want to make sure we have
that one covered. Um the [clears throat]
next one is actually less of a question
and um just trying to maybe update some
people because you know we here we have
this meeting happening today. We have
the board meeting later and then we have
a training uh committee in a week or so
that um you know that there are ongoing
discussions regarding how much um you
know end of life uh didactic is in there
and how much um you know practicum care
is um um in in there. I just wanted to
kind of bring up the question of, you
know, for practicum care, um, if there
are people in the states that are
potentially, um, up for do helping with
that training, um, in their situations.
It it's come up and I don't want to put
anyone on the spot here, but that, you
know, hospice care might be a good way
for for doing that and different ones.
So, just opening up the issue of like
what is our capability in the state to
have people do end of life practicums.
And and if no one has any comments, I'll
just kind of leave it as a open issue
that we'll have to look at that if
people if we're thinking that it's
important that people get end of life
experience about how to um facilitate
that experience in our
Next thing that's written on here is
access to psilocybin um psilocybin
mushrooms. Um by any chance is Chris on
the call from the propagation committee.
So, one question that's I've been asked
to me and other people is will there be
um you know psilocybin uh mushrooms
available come January and again people
do may have a lot more information than
I do. I've talked to at least one grower
that um is planning on getting licensed
so I don't think that's going to be a
barrier is is my answer and if anyone
else has any other information to share.
>> Larry I can actually propose or I can
actually provide a little bit of
information. We've actually had at this
point three different potential
cultivators who have reached out and we
are uh simply working on the application
um program itself and actually should
have that here within the next week week
and a half available for the public. And
uh what we've said in several of the
other meetings is that anybody who is
interested in that of course can go to
the current rules that have been
promulgated see what exactly those
requirements are and then um just so
people know it will be an online
application process that they'll be able
to go through. So if they start
gathering those documents and
requirements they'll have it. And with,
for example, with the potential
cultivators, what we already have is
several of them have been asking us
questions, ensuring that they have the
right documents, inspections, all that
sort of thing in advance. And so I'm
actually very confident that we'll have
uh that we'll have at least a producer,
if not multiple producers shortly.
>> Tom, thanks so much for sharing. That's
great news. Good to know that. Um, next
question. That's uh
>> um sorry, Dr. Leman. Sky had her hand
up.
>> Oh, I'm sorry.
>> Go ahead, Sky.
>> Yeah, real quick. Um we wanted to know
how long it takes once you put in an
application for a grower or anything
down the line. How long it What is the
time frame to get approved?
>> Sure, I can answer that, Sky. Um,
essentially once they have submitted the
application and if they have all of the
other inspections, for example, they
have to have a certificate of occupancy,
etc. Uh, as long as they have all of
that in order, we then at that point um,
and the documents are there and we've
done our review and we've verified them,
which will not take very long. We're
talking a couple of business days to
really be able to do that kind of
verification. um we schedule a um a site
visit and go out and do a visit. And so
we really should at least for these
first several um it really should only
take a few weeks to a month. Um the
first one or two of course will probably
take a little longer because it is a
little bit of a new process. Um but we
are anticipating that it'll be fairly
quickly. [snorts]
>> Thank you.
>> Absolutely. Not a problem.
>> Go ahead, Ian.
>> Yes. Yes. And then I just had one more
question, Dominic. I know you just got
off the um camera, but uh it is still
the department's plan to not charge fees
on those licenses.
>> Uh thank you, Ian. That is correct. Um
there is the statute does not actually
give us authority to charge fees and so
that is not a part of the process.
Which by the way, I should say though
does not mean that there aren't other
fees for example for other inspections
or other aspects. It's just the
Department of Health has no peace.
>> Any other comments on
that topic? If if not, I'll go on to the
next one.
>> Sky did have her hand up.
>> Go ahead, Sky.
>> I'm so sorry. I don't know why I can't
get on today. Um, do you have any idea
what the other fees would be or where I
could find that out
pertaining to what we just discussed?
>> Thank you, Scott. It
>> Yeah, it does depend on what counties or
mun municipalities um where the business
is located or the location. So, that
does vary and change based upon those.
Um, we don't have a listing of what all
of those fees potentially are. Um, but
they would be normal fees associated,
for example, with getting a business
license, you know, registering, you
know, those sort of things. But you
could go in and if you wanted to see
what that would look like is if you look
at that current promulgated rule, you
could see what agencies other agencies
are involved in being able to, you know,
what you would need to do in contacting
them in order to find out what their
fees are.
>> Thanks, Dominic. I appreciate it.
>> Absolutely.
Any
other questions at this point or
comments?
I wanted to bring up the issue of
liability insurance because I've been
hearing about this um several providers
or potential providers have um have
brought that brought this up and um so
again this is for open discussion
particularly if people have any
information on what's happening in
Colorado now. But the question really is
about the potential availability of uh
malpractice or other general other
liability insurance for um licensed
providers or facilitators.
Denali, do you happen to have any
information on that just either in your
role as a lawyer or working with half
Can't find her.
>> Go ahead, Ann. I can't find
>> Denali.
>> Yeah, no worries. Um, so I've been a
licensed insurance producer for a few
years. Um,
typically what we see in liability
policies is that they have a specific
exclusion for deliberate or purposeful
criminal acts. Um, and so they don't
look at is it legal in New Mexico. They
look at is it illegal anywhere. So,
because the statute is illegal in
federal law, typically
insured insurers will just exempt it
out. Um, I don't have any specific
information on Colorado, though.
>> Go ahead, Denali.
>> Hi. Sorry, I accidentally
disconnected and so missed a little bit
of the introduction to this topic, but
um is the question about what the where
providers what providers might be
available in Colorado,
>> Colorado or New Mexico?
>> Yeah.
Yeah. Um, so I'm happy to share the
information of what's been what
providers have used in um in Colorado
and other places, folks operating in New
Mexico, um there's a there's a unique
challenge because in in addition to what
Ian was just walking through with um
this exclusion, you know, it it's the
question is where does your medical
malpractice insurance end? Um, and the
question I I think that the answer is
going to be um, you know, as soon as
you're actually touching something
that's federally illegal. And so what's
needed is supplemental insurance. Um and
so for dylic licensed people which all
of most of pe most of the people who are
operating in New Mexico will be right
someone who who already covers
professional liability insurance for
their medical services and then
separately needs to have gap coverage
insurance for any any claims that might
arise from
the um actual uh ingestion and uh of of
psilocybin.
um what we've been seeing so the the um
National Psychedelic Association NPA um
has developed a an insurance product for
that gap and there's a couple of other
providers but the the the biggest name
in the space is the national um
psychedelic association and that has
been an initiative that's been underway
for the last couple of years. So I'm
happy to develop a list including NPA
and others and and see what's
recommended specifically for people who
are dyicensed, right, who otherwise have
professional liability insurance for for
their health care um and behavioral
health services.
>> Go ahead, Larry.
>> Yeah. Um Dal, do you have any idea about
the the expense? I know I've heard
people in New Mexico say that adding
ketamine services onto their current
malpractice may cost an extra two or
three thousand. I'm just curious if um
any estimates on let's say you were a um
psychiatrist or primary care physician
that already had malpractice how much
more it would cost to uh to get that
additional rider from
>> Oh, I'm glad Dr. Rosen your your hand
shot up. I was going to ask you to chime
in. Do you have any idea? I'm not aware,
but I was going to put ask Dr. Rosen if
he knows from his experience.
>> Go ahead, Dr.
>> There's there's Thank you. Yeah, there's
no there's no there was no change in our
malpractice. So, it's it's under it's
under and same with medical aid and
dying. I think the issue here is that
this is a substance that is illegal,
right? So, if I decide I'm going to
start prescribing heroin, right, and not
this, you know, or or some LSD, those
are illegal substances federally.
They're they're schedule one. So you
have to get a special schedule one
license for that. But ketamine is a very
legal medication. So there's no
difference. And same with all the
medications are included in the medical
aid and dying cocktail. So I think the
issue here is a this is a an illegal
substance that I am prescribing to a
patient federally.
>> Go ahead.
>> Yeah. And um that was that was my guess
too. Um and that's where this this new
issue of gap coverage comes. So where
the medical malpractice insurance ends
and some new insurance product for um
you know this uniquely challenging space
that is covering
care that um you know is federally
illegal. I I do believe that those
insurance products because of the
complexity um they've been pretty um
pretty pricey, but I'm happy to pull
from um from other states what what
those rates are and um yeah, what people
are considering.
Ian.
>> Yeah, I think this definitely would need
some sort of
rule or um
law from OSI or the legislature. Um
because
under like even if there was a policy
that said we're going to cover
psychedelic malpractice
in reality if it hit if it hit the
courts and they had to decipher
it would probably end in favor of the
insurer not having to pay because it
still was an illegal action. Um, so I
definitely think that would probably be
under the jurisdiction of the OSI, uh,
the office of the superintendent of
insurance to create a surplus line
product, um, for psychedelic psychedelic
medical malpractice. Um because I can't
see any other way that a court could
compel an insurer to pay for a federally
like illegal action. Um
but I I am not a lawyer. Um
thank you.
>> This is Larry. Um a question for Denali
again. I know I keep picking on you
today, so thanks for all your help. Um
let's say that as it looks likely that
um that synthesized psilocybin becomes
uh you know let's say a schedule three
medicine within 6 months and so it's
still a prescription item. Would that um
would that then deal with the issue or
would there still be a concern that it's
a schedule three substance?
>> Yeah. Um that's that then I think puts
it in the same realm as um Dr. Rosen
mentioned with ketamine, right? And so
it would still fall under um your
existing medical malpractice plan. Um I
just one thing to keep in mind, right,
we know the parameters parameters of the
state program exclude FDA approved um
products, right? And so what is
happening within the state program will
always be unless there is change to
to the law natural mushroom um which you
know doesn't doesn't have a pathway for
federal approval. It could be
rescheduled as we're seeing with
cannabis but um FDA synthetic psilocybin
will not have an impact on providers
operating within the state program with
natural mushroom.
Not only would would you anticipate a
situation where psilocybin
the chemical you know byona or compass
becomes schedule three and and the DEA
still views psilocybin mushrooms as
schedule one? Seems a little bizarre
because the schedule one basically
requires that you um have no medical
utility. So that seems like a it already
seems bizarre but it would be
particularly bizarre in that situation.
I agree that it would be bizarre and I
think that that is the most likely thing
to
come right. You will have FDA approval
of a product either Eona or Compass's
um products or both and the natural
mushroom will remain schedule one. I
mean, that's um I think there were even
some FDA analoges to cannabis um many
decades ago and and you know, we're just
seeing rescheduling now. Um so I I think
it is likely that um the natural
mushroom will remain schedule one even
while we see FDA
um approval. I I cross my fingers that
that is not the case. But um
>> I think too there's you know some
competing interests and the in you know
how do I say this right that I I think
pharma has an interest in the natural
mushroom remaining schedule one because
then access is through this um through
whatever their synthetic product is. And
so I just want to name that that that
that's a part of um this whole train
that's moving quickly ahead.
>> Go ahead, Ian.
>> Yeah, and I just wanted to agree with
Denali. Um draabinol, which is Delta 9
tetrahydroanabidol,
um is an approved schedule 3 medication,
has been since 1985
or six. um
perfectly legal but if it comes from a
plant that's where the problem comes. So
I would expect the federal government to
do a similar thing and say okay well
psilocybin or psilicin is uh legal but
the mushrooms not so much.
I would just say I think I know the
people who will challenge that um you
without saying their names who've
challenged before I don't know what will
happen legally but but based on the uh
based on the the obvious medical benefit
when you've done that so be interesting
how that plays out.
Any other comments on liability
insurance? Um if not, I I think we've
covered um everything on the agenda, but
um the last topic was add your own. So
um both for people on the committee or
public a comment. Are there other
issues, logistical issues relevant to
starting up um and the question was
homebased psilocybin therapy, but it
could be any any end of life.
Oh, also as an aside before we do that,
did you want me to um just show that
clip piece sent real quick?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. This is a little uh
entertainment here. So, um um I think as
people know, we um we're starting up
groups psilocybin uh research using the
whole mushroom and chocolate at UNM for
PTSD with veterans. And um I thought I'd
show an 18-second clip about um our room
and what a group therapy room looks
like.
Okay,
>> this is your entertainment interlude.
>> Hopefully it's not terribly
grainy. All right. Uh, can you see that?
>> Yeah.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay, cool.
>> There's five people that fit in this
room.
One of the challenges is ceilings in
institutional. So, we have clouds and
and uh various hangings up there to make
it into a friendly space.
Thanks for showing that.
Um any other uh comments, questions,
anything of that or if not we can uh end
our meeting a little bit early. I know a
lot of us are going to the meeting this
afternoon, but we definitely have time
if anyone has questions,
comments.
>> Go ahead, Joel.
>> Thank you. I'm just trying to understand
the process. So, a lot of great
comments, thoughts were brought up this
morning. H how does this get
synthesized? How do we get kind of
followup and and kind of how do these
decisions, all these questions that we
asked, how do they how do they get
decided? Is this I mean I know we're you
know this is an advisory committee. I
mean is this all ultimately the same
kind of conversation happens again at
the board level whatever whatever the
the main committee level or kind of what
what is this process of of kind of
clarifying all these various uh topics
that we kind of covered? I think there
would be generally agreement but but no
real closure.
>> Go ahead Ian.
>> Yeah. So what happens is the committees
discuss um we'll prepare their
recommendations. So, I'm sure Larry will
take um the information, help synthesize
it with the department. Once it gets
brought up to the board, Larry as the
chair of this committee will act as the
sponsor and we'll bring it to the board.
We have these committees so that the
public who may have conflicts of
interest, who may have other
disqualifying factors from being on the
board can still participate because we
recognize they still have expertise. Um
but it allows us to then take that to
the conflict of interest free board um
and then further deliberate ensure that
it works for the patients um and that
kind of thing. It is always uh this
meeting I believe Larry brought it up as
kind of an open forum uh so he was just
collecting input and working on that
synthesis but he can clarify more on
that.
>> Go ahead Larry.
>> Yeah. Um, thanks Ian, thanks everybody.
Um, so the the way we've been
envisioning this in the end of life
committee is that since all the other
committees and all the other issues sort
of affect us that that our rules making
would be happening sort of downstream of
training and licensing and such. But but
yeah, we're definitely keeping track of
the different issues that happen here.
Um I mean one of the ones that seems
like there's
um may benefit from other meetings
meetings happening um you know getting
legislative or legal input is is the
whole question about the uh about the
landlord thing because there sounds like
there's very strong feelings um on on
that and there's also legal concern. So
seems like that one we may need to have
some process to get more information or
get some help to see if there's a a way
out way out of that dilemma.
Chris.
>> Yeah. I think to follow up on just these
last few comments, what's the
anticipated timeline? Because certainly
through today's conversation, there's a
lot of there's probably more questions
than answers still at at this point. And
so you said you mentioned downstream of
maybe the the other regulations, but
when will the training or is are the
training regulations set? And um where
what do you mean when you say
downstream? Like next year the end of
life information will be dis talked
about and decided.
>> Thanks Chris. I I I can give my best
understanding of that. No, the I mean
there's still some very important areas
that have not gone into um rules
hearings that they're training,
education, and licensing. Um I think
there's an interest in trying to get
those solidified as soon as possible. So
that like when when we met as a board,
we identified that propagation and
training needed to be the first issues
to be addressed because we don't have a
mushroom supply and you don't have
people trained. So that's the order that
and so we're the the hope is to move um
move ahead on that once there's a
agreement and hopefully some consensus
and I think Dr. Zerlo is going to has a
comment on that too.
>> Yeah, thank you Larry. You sum that up
very well. Thank you. Um but from a
little bit more as a timeline is the
department is going to be releasing um
the proposed regulations here at the end
of the month um and uh and be scheduling
that rule hearing to happen at the end
of September early October. And so um
but the thing that uh to remind
everybody is these are not the final
rules and they will not have everything.
So for example, a lot of the questions
that have come up right now, you know,
those are things that may also not be in
these current rules, but either may be
adjusted or as we continue to have rule
process, rule hearing processes get
added in, for example, some of the
exceptions, some of the additional legal
questions as we bring those back to, for
example, our legal team, uh, you know,
they may have additional other
suggestions, but we continue to have
these open public meetings. the
committees and the board to hear
concerns, to hear issues. And the thing
to remember is when we talk about
starting the program here in December of
26, it's a start. It does not mean that
the entire program is going to be stood
up in one day, for example. It's going
to take time to continue to develop. And
so, as these questions come up, we can
look at what needs to continue to be
modified. But it also means that we'll
be able to start helping at least some
patients here beginning in December and
January. And so I hope that that helps
to explain a little bit of the process.
Um, you know, we're we continue to
listen to people. We continue to hear uh
concerns and other issues and we refer
and talk with experts all around the
country and even internationally in
order to have that. many of whom have
shown up in several of these meetings or
done presentations. Uh I know Larry for
example and Dan in the research
committee and Brenda uh on the training
and education have had quite a few
speakers and they've been really good. I
know next week in the equity meeting
there's going to be um a presentation
from Marina Robbins with regard to
Native American and traditional uh
practices. So all of those are
continuing to happen and I think there's
a little bit of misunderstanding that
once the regulations or the proposed
regulations have been promulgated that
that's it that we stop and that's not
the case at all. We will be continuing
to make revisions and adjustments and
fine-tuning and sometimes maybe even
revamping se sections if from a
practical standpoint they just aren't
working. some of them you know uh this
is a program that has not actually been
done anywhere else and so there are a
lot of aspects to it to be considering
but we're here to listen it's why we
continue to have these meetings and will
continue even after promulgation of some
of the items um and some of them are you
know we hear concerns for example with
propagation we were hearing concerns
that you know uh that nobody was going
to apply for it and as I mentioned
earlier We have several that are already
looking at that. And so, and had we not,
we would have then been immediately
looking at how do we revise this? How do
we make this more accessible or easier
without compromising safety and trying
to come up with different ways and
different ideas? So, I hope that's
helpful.
>> Ian, did you have your hand up?
He and he said what I was going to say.
>> Okay.
>> Any other thoughts or or comments?
>> I'd like to propose that our next
meeting happen on September 11th. It's
roughly a month away. Is that day good
for people? Is it available uh for for
meetings or any conflicts with other
committees?
>> Research and continuous improvement is
at 9:00.
>> How about the 18th?
>> September 18th. 18th
>> 18th looks pretty free. Let me just
double check. Um yeah. Uh yeah, we could
um yeah, nine nine on the 18th looks
good.
>> Okay. You I'm trying possible not to
have two meetings backed up with each
other. It's kind of a you know, so I
think um people are smiling about that.
So good. So let's u let's go for um 9 to
11 on the 18th then.
>> And Larry, just as a note on that, it is
very appreciated to space the meetings
out a little bit. Um and and to give
everybody an idea of how much we are
listening as you know the various
committees, the advisory board, the
department just in all of these public
scheduled meetings and all of that there
have already been over 70 of them for
the various topics. So to give an idea
of how much time is really being
invested and so I really want to give a
big shout out to everybody who has been
involved in all of this because this has
been a lot of effort a lot of work and
we really do appreciate it. We may not
always agree on various topics and
various items, but that's a part of the
the discourse, right? And so, but I
really want to appreciate everybody who
has been involved because we would not
be able to be moving the program forward
without that involvement, the the
different aspects of it, the thoughts,
the changes that occur as we move
forward. We just wouldn't be able to do
it. And I think just even from while
while hours do not necessarily mean
quality, I think the vast majority of
those hours have been extremely
uh qualitative and very helpful. Um, and
pardon me, I used the wrong word in
saying qualitative. It's already been a
little bit of a a busy morning, so my
apologies everyone, but it has
definitely been a quality set of
meetings. And most of those meetings, by
the way, have actually been between an
hour and a half to two hours. So when I
say over 70 meetings, we're really
looking at somewhere between probably
120 to 160 hours um in in public
meetings. So thank you everybody. Really
appreciate it. And uh I hope everybody
had a great weekend. And Larry, any
closing comments?
>> No, thanks. I think it's been a great
meeting. It's really nice to see us
getting into some of the logistical uh
issues and sorting it out. So look
forward to continuing it next month. Um,
we don't have a specific topic for next
month, but I'll get that worked out.
>> Uh, it looks like uh Candy has a
comment.
>> Go ahead, Candy.
>> Hi there. I have not been able to use
the chat and I saw a number of people
have been grayed out and I didn't know
how to fix that. But in short, I wanted
to just thank everyone
>> um for all the effort. Yeah.
>> Oh, sorry, Candy. Um, I just wanted to
answer as far as the chat that is
usually on the individual side with and
quite often has to do with whatever
permissions that they may have on it.
Um, we have seen that occur before when
there are people who are in it. We get a
message on our end that says for
example, some people in this chat are
outside your organization. They may have
message related policies that will apply
to the chat. Um and uh so unfortunately
there's not anything we can do about
that on the department end. But
especially if someone's joining from a
private um uh like a a um uh a different
company or organization, they may have
the have that ability grayed out or it
may just be a setting within your own
logging into it. And so you may want to
check on the settings. I'll check.
>> Yeah, that's all I that's the only
information we have on that.
>> Well, thank you. And I just wanted to
chime in and thank everyone. It's a lot
of hard work been done and it's can
continue. So, thank you.
>> Thanks everybody. See you next month.
>> Have a great Friday and weekend
everyone.
>> See some of you in a few hours.
[laughter]